So what does using the Problem Statement Worksheet
in the moment actually look like?
Well, in the moment, you're unlikely to actually — without a sheet of paper —
go through all the different components and fill it out.
But what you can do is think about what the different components
of that Problem Statement Worksheet are,
and what questions you could ask.
Let me give you a real example from this morning.
I woke up this morning and there was a water main break
outside my apartment on the Upper West Side.
And there was a problem: the street was flooded.
And so I needed to think through, in the moment,
how was I going to deal with it — and think through
what the problem is that I need to solve.
Obviously, there's a water main break, but importantly,
who are all the stakeholders that are going to be impacted?
How am I going to get to the office to do this video shoot?
How are my children going to get to school this morning?
How are the deliveries that were supposed to come that afternoon
going to be received or impacted by this water main break?
And so going through that structured approach enabled me to think through,
very rapidly in that moment, how best to address this problem.
When you're filling out the Problem Statement Worksheet in the moment,
there are a couple of mistakes that we commonly see.
One is to think about the stakeholders — and the key here
is to really ensure you've thought about all the relevant stakeholders that need to be
involved in order to actually have your recommendation be actionable.
Another is the scope of the solution set. Have you been very clear,
and is everybody aligned on what is in scope versus what is out of scope?
And the third is thinking through: what are the constraints?
And here it's being really honest
in terms of what the constraints are that one needs to solve for.
And that has implications, then, for thinking through the time and the resources
you have available, and how best to prioritise your work moving forward.
The Problem Statement Worksheet is one of the most effective tools, I think,
that we can actually use as problem solvers.
And the way that I always thought about it when I first started in my career
was, I thought: “Oh my gosh,
I have to have an answer for every single box on this robust worksheet.”
And the truth of the matter is, I think that sometimes the most powerful way
to use the tool is to use it in a dynamic, ad hoc way.
What are the ways that we can ask the right questions to tease out the answer,
even if we don't actually have the time to robustly fill it out?
The Problem Statement Worksheet should not be something
that you start on day one and never refresh.
It should be something that you actually — as you learn more about the problem,
as you understand more stakeholders —
you continue to reiterate, so that it becomes something
that's truly the latest and greatest in thinking.